yeah
yeah
so
so
withdrawal
withdrawal
In Januarylene felon.
In Januarylene felon.
An
An
Professor Chen, Dear Returnees, Dear Colleagues
陳教授各位歸兵各位同事
Welcome to today's feast of knowledge
非常歡迎各位來參加今天的知識的饗宴
The speaker we invited today is Professor Chen Dongsen from the Department of Sociology, National Taiwan University
今天我們請到的主講者是台大社會系的陳東森教授
Professor Chen Dongsen is a Bachelor of Public Health Department of National Taiwan University School of Medicine
陳東森教授是台大醫學院公衛系的學士
Later, I changed my plan and returned to the United States to study a doctorate in sociology.
後來改圖歸證到美國念了一個社會學的博士
These two are very different
這兩個相差很大
Then he returned to National Taiwan University as an associate professor in the Department of Sociology
接著他就回到台大擔任社會系的副教授
department head
系主任
When I met him, he was the head of the Department of Sociology
我在認識他的時候他是社會系系主任
At that time, the Humanities Department of the National Science Council organized a humanities and social sciences camp for high school students.
當時國科會人文處下面辦了一個高中生人文社會科學營
The camp director is Professor Chen Dongsen
營主任就是陳東森教授
I also noticed a few people today
我今天也注意到有幾位
students graduating students
學生畢業的學生
also here
也在這裡
Then he was in 2005 to 2007
接著他在2005年到2007年
Served as Director of Humanities and Social Sciences Division of National Science Council
擔任國科會人文人文及社會科學處處長
During his tenure, he has done many meaningful and remarkable things.
在他任內做了很多很有意義很了不起的事情
He also served as the editor-in-chief of Taiwan Sociology
他也擔任過台灣社會學的主編
Served as a knowledge committee member of the Institute of Chinese and Foreign Studies
擔任中外研究社會研究所的知識委員
He is also the chairman of the Taiwan Sociological Association
也是台灣社會學會的理事長
He has written a lot and has won many honors, including being the research director of the Chinese Academy of Sciences.
他著作非常多也獲得了許多榮譽包括國科學的結束研究長
One of the topics he's going to talk about today is quite theoretical.
他今天要講的一個題目是相當理論性的
I am very pleased that so many people come with such a topic
以這樣的題目有這麼多人來我已經覺得非常欣慰
I am very happy for Professor Chen
非常替陳教授感到高興了
This is a highly theoretical topic
這是一個高度理論性的題目
Compared to our previous topic
比起我們先前的這個題目
So today's topic is self-reliance and social cooperation
那麼今天的題目是自立跟社會合作
On the surface, these two topics seem to be
那麼這兩個題目表面上看起來好像是
There is Middle-earth, but in fact it has a very complicated relationship
有中土但事實上有很複雜的關係
Both Chinese and Western thought are discussing this issue
中西思想都在討論這個問題
I'm personally very interested in this question too
我個人對這個問題也非常感興趣
So we now welcome Professor Chen with warm applause
那麼我們現在以熱烈掌聲歡迎陳教授
Vice President Wang and everyone here
王副院長還有在座各位
It's very unexpected to come here to speak today.
今天來這邊演講是非常意外的
Because just now Vice President Wang introduced me to serve in the National Science Council
因為剛剛王副院長介紹我在國科會服務
In fact, I am in the National Science Council
其實我在國科會
In fact, during the service period, it was mainly due to the strong support of Vice President Wang.
服務的期間其實主要都是王副院長他的大力支持
So he wants me to come, I dare not not come
所以他要我來我是不敢不來
Although I personally feel that this speech is really heavy for me.
雖然我自己覺得這個演講對我來講實在是複擔蠻重的
So the outline of the speech prepared by the speech was changed again
所以那個演講稿準備的演講的大綱又改了
These days are changing
這幾天都在改
So it's a thankless task, but it doesn't seem like there's much choice
所以吃力不討好不過這個好像也沒什麼選擇的可能性
So I'll try to share what I know with you.
所以我就盡量把我知道的跟大家分享一下
Well, today's topic was just said by Vice President Wang to be very theoretical.
那今天這個題目剛剛這個王副院長說是很理論性的
Then I hope that what I can discuss with you is relatively simple.
那我希望我能跟大家討論的是比較簡單的
I think maybe everyone can do more or less
我想可能大家也可以多多少少
can also understand
也都可以了解
That's because the subject of this study
那因為這個研究的這個主題
The sociology I learned by myself
跟我自己學的這個社會學
The relationship can be said to be quite close
關係可以說是相當密切的
Most people may not know
那大部分人可能也不太清楚
What is Sociology about?
社會學到底是在學什麼
I always feel that studying sociology is very good at understanding society
總是覺得學社會學很了解社會
Then you look like I don't understand society
那你看我像了不了解社會
doesn't look alike
看起來也不是很像
So if you study sociology, you don't understand society
所以學社會學了不了解社會
Sometimes relationships don't have to be that way
有些時候關係不一定是那麼的
so direct
那麼的直接
Well, many of our students have studied sociology
那我們也很多學生上了這個社會學
then two
那麼兩個
after a year
上了一年以後
They don't know whether they know sociology in the end
他們也不知道是不是知道社會學到底
what are you studying
在學什麼
Then I'm talking about this Chile working with this society
那我在討論這個智利跟這個社會合作
actually
其實
there's another one there
還有一個在那裡
actually want to express
其實想要去表達
one thing to show
想要去呈現的一件事情
that is
就是說
We are in sociology or economics and political science
我們在社會學或者是經濟學政治學
The topic being discussed is nothing more than
在談的議題不外乎也是
relationship between people
人跟人之間的關係
I would look at it like this
我會這樣子來看就是說
Emphasis in economics on the competition of such markets
在經濟學強調這種市場的競爭
Emphasize that people start from a more independent perspective
強調人是從比較自立的角度出發
with sociology
跟社會學所談的
sociology is not about
社會學也不是講說
There will be no competition between people
人跟人之間不會競爭也是會的
Maybe the one he pays more attention to
可能他比較重視的那種
relationship with people
跟人之間的關係
under a team of reciprocal and trusting cooperation
是在互惠跟信任的合作的機組底下
to carry out
來進行的
So what we are more familiar with is
所以我們比較熟悉的就是
The way this market works
這個市場運作的模式
Of course competition has become what we are used to
競爭當然就變成我們也很習慣了
But we may often forget to say
但是我們可能常常忘記說
There are still many times between people
人跟人之間還是有很多時候
It is possible only through cooperation
是必須要合作才有可能的
So I'm going to just put this
所以我就暫且姑且就是把這個
Sociology Emphasis in Research
社會學在研究的重點
It's talking about reciprocity and cooperation
是在談這個互惠跟合作
that economics
那這個經濟學
Let's take it more like we're talking about this competition
我們就把它當成比較像在談這個競爭
Then our small examination institute sales talk about political science
那我們這個小考院銷售說政治學
Political thought is also broad spirit
政治思想也是博大精神
Then what I want to talk about is the distribution of power
那我想比較談的是在那一種權力的分配上面
So under a power structure
所以在一個權力結構底下
Probably because of this kind of subordinate relationship
大概就是有這種上下從屬的關係
So what is the relationship between these three different people?
所以這三種不同的人跟人之間的關係呢
I think it is the aspect that these three disciplines may attach importance to
我想是這三個學科可能它重視的這個面向
not the same
不太一樣
So I will talk about this Chile working with this society
所以我會談這個智利跟這個社會合作
Of course, I am also trying to solve some very fundamental problems.
當然也是在想處理一些很根本的這個問題
Then I don't think it's easy for me to make a fuss
那我想我也不好頒門弄腐
But in the seventeenth century the philosopher Hobbes
不過在十七世紀的哲學家霍布斯
This Vavius ​​he wrote is this spiritism
他寫的這個Vavius就是這個聚靈論
In fact, he has clearly mentioned
其實他已經很清楚的提到
It's just that people are Chilean selfish
就是人是智利的 自私的
I put selfishness with chile and i don't put him off for now
我把自私跟智利我暫時不把他
He makes a very clear distinction just for himself
他做很明確的區分 就是為了自己
for yourself you have to survive
為了自己你要生存
In the discussion of Hobbes
在霍布斯的討論裡面
People follow each other in order to maintain their own survival
人跟人是為了維持自己的生存
this endless war
這個無窮盡的戰爭
what do you want peace
你要和平怎麼辦呢
People can only cede power to this country
人只有把權力讓渡給這個國家
Govern by the state to maintain an order
由國家來治理 維持一個秩序
make these chileans
使得這些智利的人
He was able to be in a relatively peaceful state like this
他能夠在一個比較和平的這種狀態
Come spend a day like ours
來度過一個像我們這樣
full of order full of stability
滿有秩序 滿穩定的
this way of life
這種生活的方式
Hobbes' view
霍布斯的這個看法
Of course it represents
當然代表的是
is why the country exists
就是國家為什麼要存在
Why do countries exist
國家為什麼要出現
very important reason
很重要的一個理由
But I think it might be a pity
不過我想可能有點可惜
Hobbes if he looked further ahead
霍布斯如果他再往前看一點
From looking at it is the development of human society
從看看就是人類社會發展的
this origin of history
這一種歷史的這個元起
before there was no country
在沒有國家之前
In fact, many of these primitive societies
其實很多的這一種元初社會
Anthropological research clearly shows that
人類學的研究很清楚可以看到
Actually it's not in Infinity War
其實它不是在無窮境的戰爭
They can keep the peace in a variety of ways
他們透過各式各樣的方式是可以維持和平的
One of the most important is the exchange of physical
其中最重要的一個就是理物的交換
Anthropologists
這個理物的交換在人類學家
A famous anthropologist named Marsha Schellings
很著名的一個人類學家叫Marsha Schellings
He mentioned in the study of the original society that
他在研究原出的社會裡面提到說
The origin of physical exchange is actually
理物的交換的原起其實就是
You are in a situation where everyone is working hard
你在大家都致力的這種情況底下
How do you avoid endless war
你如何避免無窮境的戰爭
The best thing to do is lay down your weapons
最好的辦法就是放下你的武器
Give the other person a gift to show your kindness
給對方一個禮物表達你的善意
If the other party stands at this reciprocal angle
如果對方站在這種互惠的角度
He also answered your words of a gift
他也回正你一個禮物的話
Ongoing exchange of such gifts
持續的這種禮物的交換
Only peace can continue to operate
只可以讓和平可以不斷地運作下去
i talk about hobbes
我講這個霍布斯
tell this anthropologist
講這個人類學家
Actually what I want to mention is that
其實我要提的就是說
even at the beginning
人即便一開始
he may survive
他可能為了生存
For the reproduction of the race
為了族群的這種繁衍
he may be self-reliant
他可能是自立的
may be selfish
可能是自私的
After all, there is some mechanism
那終究是有一些機制
There are ways to make that cooperation
有一些辦法可以使得那個合作
He can develop gradually
他是可以逐漸的慢慢的發展出來的
That's the foreword
那這個是前言
Talk a little bit about the previous one
講一點點前面的這樣子的一個
one origin one history
一個原起一個歷史
Then if we go back to comparing
那如果我們回到比較
This discussion in modern times
近代的這個討論
that was in 1968
那在1968年
this is an economist
這個是經濟學家
I don't know much about economics
經濟學其實我懂得也不多
But this economist
不過這個經濟學家
1968 The Harding
1968年這個Harding
he in this one
他在這個一個
This publication is very important in academia
在學術界算是很重要的這個刊物
Science1968
Science 1968年
He brought up this tragedy about public wealth
他提出了就是有關於公共財的這個悲劇
an argument like this
這樣子的一個論點
If people are independent
人如果都是自立的
that no one would do for public affairs
那沒有人會為了公共的事務
any effort for the public good
公共財付出任何的努力
Because this public property means
因為這個公共財的意思是說
as long as others do
只要別人做了
then you can enjoy
那你一定可以享用
Someone else cleaned up the park
別人去把這個公園掃乾淨了
then you can enjoy a clean
那你就可以享受到乾淨的
beautiful this park
漂亮的這個公園
then you can't
那你不可能
if you are intellectual
如果你是智力的
then why are you paying
那你為什麼要付出呢
The house has been cleaned
人家已經打掃好了
then you don't do anything
那你什麼事都不要做
you can do it and enjoy it
你就可以做享其成
For those who are intelligent
那智力的人來講
must be hitchhikers
都一定是搭便車的
So from this Harding
那所以從這個 Harding
present this tragedy of the commons
提出這個公共財的這個悲劇
after
之後
Later there was a lot of this debate
後來有很多的這個辯論
that is
就是說
if everyone is intelligent
如果每個人都智力的
How about this kind of public affairs?
那這一種公共的這個事務怎麼辦呢
then
那當時呢
probably only two options
大概只有兩個選項
One is to find out the country again
一個就是把國家再找出來
find the country again
把國家再找出來
That is when we also often refer to
那就是在我們也常常提到
If public facilities related to public interest
如果跟公共利益有關的公共設施
tax increase by the state
就由國家來增稅
to provide
來提供
Lest everyone is unwilling to pay
免得大家都不願意付錢
or unwilling to do something
或者不願意做出一些什麼事情
Or donate a little more to provide this public facility
或多捐一點來提供這種公共的設施
by the state
由國家來做
may be a good way
可能是一個好的方式
The other is to let the market
另外一個就是讓市場
Turn this public thing into privatization
把這個公共的東西都變成是私有化
everyone you want to use
每個人你要用的
If you can define private property
如果能夠定義私有的財產
After you define this clearly
你就把這個定義清楚之後
You treat everyone who wants to use him as property
每個人要用的你就把他當成財產
to use
來使用
you know you have to pay the price
你就很清楚的要付出這些代價
Of course we also know that there are many things
當然我們也知道有很多東西
He has no way to treat it as a private property
他是沒有辦法當成是一個私有財的
Like the air or the ocean
比如像空氣或者是海洋
you can't define
你根本是沒有辦法定義的
So Harding mentions the tragedy of the commons
所以 Harding提到公共財的悲劇
in 1968
在 1968 年
options he could discuss at that time
他那個時候能夠討論到的選項
Probably the market and the country
大概就是市場跟國家
But after Harding
但是在 Harding 之後
There is probably an important
大概也有一個很重要的
The political economist is this OSShuang
政治經濟學家是這個奧斯爽
This is the winner of the 2009 Nobel Prize in Economics
這個是2009年諾貝爾經濟學獎的得主
the lady
這位女士
she is a public economist
她是一個公共經濟學家
a political scientist
也算是一個政治學家
Then her most important work in 1995
那她在她最1995年很重要的一個作品
public resource governance
就是對於公共資源治理
Or in the book on the governance of public property
或者是公共財的這個治理的這個著作裡面
She clearly mentioned that
她很清楚的就提到說
There are not only two options, the country and the market
不是只有國家跟市場這兩個選項
In fact, there are other possibilities
事實上是還有其他的這個可能性
There is another possibility
還有其他的這個可能性
So she spent a lot of space in this book
所以她在這個書裡面她花了很多的這個篇幅
Criticizing and discussing why the market
在批評 在討論說為什麼市場
Why the state is not necessarily more effective than anything
為什麼國家都不見得比什麼東西更有效
than the average public
比一般的這個公眾 一般的這個民眾
Discuss by yourself
自己討論
Self-discussion means what kind of norms we want to set
自己討論就是說我們要設定怎麼樣的這個規範
Then how do we make this public resource
然後我們怎麼樣讓這個公共資源
That's called maintaining together
那叫一起來維護
This is actually possible
這樣子事實上是有可能的
Then this post by Oshuang
那這個Oshuang的論柱
In fact, very attentive
事實上是非常用心的
He spent about thirty years
他大概花了三十幾年的時間
There are about 3,000 collected around the world
收集全世界大概有三千個
about the use of public resources
有關於公共資源的使用
So these 3,000 examples are from about hundreds of years ago
那這個三千個例子是從大概幾百年前
in the mountains of switzerland
在瑞士的山上
forest in japan
在日本的森林
this ranch in switzerland
瑞士的這個牧場
to this modern
到這個近代
his own doctoral dissertation
他自己的博士論文
He is studying this Los Angeles
他是研究這個洛杉磯
This throughout the Los Angeles area
整個洛杉磯地區的這個
use of groundwater
地下水的使用
he established a center
他成立了一個中心
those thirty years
那三十幾年
Just keep collecting all kinds of cases
就不斷地在收集各式各樣的這個案例
watching say
在看說
Discussed by members of the community themselves
由社區的公眾自己來討論
under what circumstances
什麼樣的情況底下
will succeed
會成功
What kind of conditions
那什麼樣的這個條件底下
he is unlikely to succeed
他不太可能會成功
The achievements of these thirty years
那這三十幾年的成果
It is very clear in this book that
在這本書裡面很清楚的呈顯出來
I just said that I avoided being too abstract
我剛剛講說我避免講的太抽象
so i took it in the book
所以我就以它在書本上
in its works
在它的作品裡面
The example where it's often mentioned
其中它經常會提到的這個例子
this one in Türkiye
就是在土耳其的這個
This fishing village in Alunya is probably at this location
阿倫亞的這個漁村大概是在這個位置
in the mediterranean at this location
在地中海在這個位置
Everyone has a little bit of this concept on the map
這個大家有一點地圖上的這個概念
Enough
就好了
If you have this iPhone you can take it out and locate it
如果你有這個 iPhone 你可以拿出來定位一下
see where it is
看看它到底在哪裡
how far is it from us
離我們這邊有多遠
this alanya this place
這個阿倫亞這個地方
Some field research done by Oswang himself
這個 Oswang 自己做的一些田野的研究
This fishing village has about 100 people
這個漁村它大概有100個人
There are 100 people
有100個人
It is a local cooperative that produces
它當地是有一個生產的合作社
But in the 1970s
不過在這個1970年代的時候
because of this market
因為這個市場
Also, the fishermen want to increase their income
還有就是說這個漁民大家要增加收入
So a lot to catch this catch
所以大量的去補撈這個漁獲
There is no limit to the amount of catch
那沒有限制補撈的這種數量
In order to snatch better fishing spots
大家為了強奪更好的補漁的地點
so there's a lot of conflict
所以有很多的衝突
a lot of conflict
很多的衝突
And more importantly because you keep replenishing
而且更重要的是因為你不斷的補
There is no way for everyone in this fishing group to reply within a period of time
大家這個漁群沒有辦法在一段時間裡面可以回復
So you heal and you become smaller
所以你補愈補愈小
Then this amount is less and less
然後補的這個數量越來越少
The fishing time is getting longer and longer
那補漁的時間越來越長
So it's hard for everyone to live
所以大家都很難活下去
So in this 1970s with such a big problem
所以在這個1970年代碰到這麼大的這個問題
Then this fishery is of course a public resource
那這個漁場當然是一個公共的資源
is owned by everyone
是大家共同所擁有的
then what should we do
那怎麼辦呢
If everyone goes to make up for it
如果大家都去爛補的話
Make it up in small fishing
在小的漁都把它補起來
Then do this like this
那這個這樣弄下去
you can't get any catch
你不可能得到任何的漁獲
that's in alanya
那在阿倫亞這個地方
These 100 fishermen want to say the question goes on like this
這100個漁民想說這個問題這樣繼續下去
is unsolvable
是無解的
Then everyone may starve to death
那大家可能都要餓死
so what about them
所以他們呢
They because we just mentioned
他們因為我們剛剛提到
They have a co-op here that produces this
他們在這裡有一個這個生產的合作社
So they decided to say
所以他們就決定說
This member in this production cooperative
在這個生產合作社裡面的這個成員
Let's find this local resident
大家把當地的這個居民找來
let's discuss
一起討論一下
Let's see how to solve such a problem
看看怎麼樣來解決這樣一個問題
so they made some effort
所以他們做了一些努力
They put this in this fish factory where they fish
他們把這個他們捕魚的這個魚廠
Because more than 100 people they probably
因為100多個人他們大概
two people have a fish boat
兩個人有一艘魚船
There are about 50 of these fishing boats
大概有50多艘的這個魚船
What about the more than 100 people?
那這100多個人呢
he put this fish factory
他把這個魚廠
Because it is the fishing factory in the offshore
因為是近海的這個捕魚的這個魚廠
They split it into about 50 different locations
他們就把它分割成大概50個不同的這個位置
50 different locations
50個不同的位置
in this position
在這個位置
By way of lottery
透過抽籤的這種方式
decide who is in which fishery
決定說誰在哪一個漁場
to go fishing
去進行捕魚的動作
But the location of the fishery where the fish are caught every day
但是每天捕魚的漁場位置
is moving every day
是每天移動的
September of the current year to January of the following year
當年的九月到隔年的一月
the fisherman moved west
漁夫就往西邊移
Move one fishing ground west
往西邊移一個漁場
Then from January to May of the following year
然後隔年的一月到五月
He moved from west to east again
他又從西邊往東邊移
like this
這樣子的話
everyone has a chance
大家都有機會
in the most fished fishing grounds
在漁獲最多的漁場
to go fishing
去進行捕魚的動作
I describe here
我在這邊描述
looks very simple
看起來是非常簡單
but what is the important thing
可是很重要的一件事情是什麼
these fishermen
就是這些漁民
They are willing to put their local fishing experience
他們願意把自己在當地捕魚的經驗
The information fully shares it out
這些資訊完全把它分享出來
Otherwise you're cutting up the fishery
否則的話你要切割這個漁場
to this fishing
對這個漁
with this reflux of his
與他的這個回流
Or the one he passed by
或者是說他經過的這個
The state of the fish factory
魚廠的這種狀況
it must be fully understood
它必須要充分的瞭解
So they cut the fish factory in fact
所以他們在切割魚廠事實上
Not so ideal when starting to cut
開始切的時候並不是那麼理想
It's been almost two years
大概經過了差不多將近兩年的時間
There is a way to clearly distinguish
才有辦法很清楚的區分出來
the location of those fish factories
那些魚廠的位置
Then the way the fish factory distributes like this
然後魚廠分配的這樣子的一個方式
So there's this mutual trust
所以大家有這種相互的信任
willing to provide information
願意把資訊提供出來
In fact, this is a very important
其實這個是一個非常重要
very important basis
非常重要的一個基礎
Of course this Oshon is not so romantic
當然這個 Oshon 沒有那麼的浪漫
That is, we all trust each other
就是大家相互之間有信任
management of public resources
就可以使得對於公共資源的管理
follow pay
跟付出
Everyone will abide by the rules like that
大家就會遵守那樣子的規則
incomplete
不完全
He went on to mention
他就接著提到說
In the governance of this public resource
在這種公共資源的治理
Discuss a set of rules from bottom to top
由下往上大家討論出一套規則
Discuss a set of norms
討論出一套規範
the rules of the game
遊戲的這個規則
then he must
那他必須要
supervised mechanism
有監督的機制
But the lower the cost of the monitoring mechanism, the better
可是監督的機制的成本越低越好
So these 50 fisheries are open seas
所以這50個漁場是開放的海域
One by one
一個接一個
So if you draw fish or the richest fishery
所以如果你抽到魚或最豐富的漁場
You will definitely be the earliest time you can start fishing
你一定會最早時間可以開始捕魚的時候
you go to the fishing ground
你就到漁場上
So if someone goes poaching your designated fishery
所以如果有誰去偷捕你指定的漁場
if fishing over there
在那邊捕魚的話
will be caught
一定會被抓到
So the monitoring mechanism
所以監督的機制
it's the way that comes with the fish farm cut
它是伴隨著漁場切割的方式
It sounds very simple when I put it this way
我這樣講聽起來是非常簡單
But in system design
可是在制度設計上
If your kind of management of public resources
如果你對公共資源的那種管理
You need to design a system that people can use
你要設計出一個大家能夠使用
And in the process of using
而且在使用的過程
Supervised mods
監督的模組
The monitoring mechanism is embedded in it
監督的機制就內含在裡面
It's actually very, very difficult
事實上是非常非常困難的
after being caught
被抓到以後
what to do
要怎麼辦
What to do after being caught
被抓到以後怎麼辦呢
Of course this OSWANG must have a punishment mechanism
當然這個 OSWANG 一定要有懲罰的機制
But his punishment mechanism is very special
可是他的懲罰機制非常特別
He said that his punishment mechanism should have two characteristics
他說他的懲罰機制要有兩個特徵
one is immediate punishment
一個是立即處罰
Second, the punishment should not be too severe
第二個那個處罰不能太重
just a light punishment
就是輕微的處罰
So if you get caught the first time
所以如果你第一次被抓到
poaching people in fishing grounds
在漁場偷捕人家
If you fish in a place other than your designated fishing ground
不是你指定漁場的地方捕魚的話
how to deal with it
那怎麼處分呢
Probably by the chairman of this cooperative
大概就是由這個合作社的主席
he is in this village
他就是在這個村裡
that's the place
就是那個地方
They are like our small villages in Taiwan
他們就像我們台灣的小鄉村
long radio station
有里長的廣播電台
just announce it on the radio
就在廣播電台宣告一下說
This so-and-so went fishing today
這個某某某今天跑到人家哪裡去捕魚
so say it this way
這樣就這樣講一下
No money or anything
也沒有罰他錢也沒有罰他什麼
Because OSWANG knows one thing very well
因為 OSWANG 他很清楚知道一件事情
punishment is of course good
處罰當然很好
because we'll talk about that later
因為我們等一下會談到
But you have to know that the punishment is too severe
但是你要知道處罰的過重
Those who are punished will turn their faces
被處罰的人是會翻臉的
he will take revenge
他是會報復的
So this will make this penalty
所以這個會使得這個處罰
the possible effect of
可能產生的這個效果
is relatively limited
是比較有限的
We can continue with everyone later
我們等一下可以跟大家繼續再
discuss this issue
討論這個問題
then i just mentioned this
那我剛剛提到這個
In fact, it is simply to put this OSWANG
其實是簡略的把這個OSWANG
its 30 years
它30幾年來
The result of this research
研究的這個成果
Summed up about eight
大概歸納了八個
This approach to public governance
對於公共治理的這種方式
From the bottom up to the community
是由下往上有社區
Eight Basic Principles of Planning in Four Episodes
四集來規劃的八個基本的原則
doesn't look like much
看起來沒什麼太大的
This knowledge is in fact
這個學問不過其實
if you think about it
如果你仔細想想
This content is very very exciting
這個內容是非常非常的精彩
wonderful enough to get this
精彩到可以得到這個
Nobio speaks
Nobio講
So OSWANG
那所以OSWANG
He said to crack this
他說要破解這個
This tragedy of public wealth
公共財的這個悲劇
between members
就是成員之間
He must be able to communicate
他要有溝通的能力
Because we just mentioned this cut of this fish farm
因為我們剛剛提到這個魚場的這個切割
He needs to communicate with each other
彼此之間他要有溝通
on this possibility
論的這個可能
And he also has some
而他也要有一些
So build members of this community
所以建立這個社區裡面的成員
mechanism of mutual trust
相互信任的機制
So you're going to be reciprocal
所以你要進行要互惠
we must work together
大家要一起合作
There is no way to avoid this trust
這個信任是沒有辦法避免的
Of course we also know
我們當然也知道
operating in a market
在一個市場的運作
In fact, he must also have a trust mechanism
事實上他也必須要有信任的機制
no mechanism for trust
沒有信任的機制
The market can't work either
市場也不可能運作
It is impossible for the state to function
國家也不可能運作
So this mechanism of trust
所以這個信任的機制
is very important
是非常重要的
have to communicate
要有溝通
There must be a mechanism for trust
要有信任的機制
Where does this trust mechanism come from?
這個信任的機制從哪裡來
because they are a small village
因為他們是一個小鄉村
they used to have this cooperative
他們曾經有這種合作社
so there may be some
所以可能有一些
can trust each other
彼此可以相互信任
or
或者是說
There may be some kinship among them
他們中間可能有一些親屬的關係
Possibility to build trust
建立了信任的可能性
Of course they also have to understand
當然他們也必須要了解
Because of their shared use of resources
他們因為共同使用資源
less and less catches
漁獲量越來越少
Everyone spends more and more time fishing
大家出去捕魚的時間越來越長
lower and lower income
收入越來越低
that common fate
那這個共同的命運
so that everyone should be able to clearly understand
使得大家應該是可以很清楚的了解
Then Ostron also mentioned that
那Ostron也提到就是說
The country's public resources on this entire Youschool.com
這個國家在這個整個遊校網上的公共資源
mechanism of self-governance
自我治理的機制
The best thing to do is not to give too much of this intervention
最好的辦法是不要給予太多的這個干預
Provide this local community opportunity
提供這個當地的這個社區機會
give this opportunity and time
給予這個機會跟時間
Let this public of this community develop their own
讓這個社區的這個公眾發展出他們自己
This specification governing this common resource
治理這個公共資源的這個規範
In fact, he still has many very exciting discussions.
那其實他還有很多非常精彩的這個討論
very very wonderful discussion
非常非常精彩的這個討論
Including that if your country really wants to manage
包括說你這個國家如果真的要管的話
Then you have to make sure your information is not enough
那你必須要確定你資訊是不是充分
you want to make sure you punish
你要確定你處罰
Are you punishing the right person?
你處罰是不是能夠處罰對的人
this is very important
這個非常重要
because you punished the wrong person
因為你處罰錯的人的話
will lead to more opportunism
會造成更多的投機主義
He can even figure it out
他甚至也可以算得出來
If someone breaks the law today
如果今天有人違反法規的話
you can't help
你沒有辦法
Immediate and correct penalty over 75%
即時的而且正確的懲罰75%以上
State intervention will only lead to more arrests
國家介入只會造成更多的頭緝
More violations of the law
更多違反法令的行為
So he once cited in the book
所以他曾經在書裡面也舉
Canadian government intervenes with the Eskimos of the North
加拿大政府介入北方的愛斯基摩人
Do Catch Control Canada's Fisheries Agency Gets Involved
做漁獲管制加拿大的漁業署介入
The result is a mess
結果一塌糊塗
So he is in this book
所以他在這本書
my personal opinion
我的個人的看法
I think OSRON is more like a sociologist
我覺得 OSRON 比較像社會學家
But this is of course our own interpretation and interpretation.
不過這個當然是我們自己的解讀跟詮釋
The important thing is that
重要的是在於
Why is he more like a sociologist?
為什麼說他比較像社會學家是
He emphasized that this bottom-up
他強調的是這個由下往上的
This kind of communication and discussion
這種溝通跟討論
short-term intelligence
可以使得短期的這種智力
Transformed into everyone taking into account the interests of the public
轉變成大家考慮到公共的這個利益
Finally of course to everyone
最後當然對每一個人
detached from one's own interests
離人自己的這一種利益的
maintenance of long-term interests
長遠利益的這一種維持
is helpful
是有幫助的
Then this communication and discussion
那這個溝通跟討論
can let us understand
可以讓我們了解說
our chile
我們那個智利
Sometimes it's too short-sighted
有些時候看的是太短視
only focus on the present
只著重在當下
How much can I gain today
今天能有多少收穫
try not to
盡量不
catch as much as possible
能夠得到的漁獲盡量的撈
but did not expect
但是沒有想到
possibly to ourselves in the long run
可能長遠對我們自己
is bad
是不好的
But after these discussions
可是經過這些溝通討論
it is possible for us to understand
有可能讓我們理解
The public interest is relatively long-term
那個公共的利益比較長遠的
the public interest
這個公共利益
how to build it
怎麼樣把它建立起來
so if we look at
所以如果我們看
I turned to public property
我轉對公共財的
This kind of discussion of this public resource
這個公共資源的這一種討論
we probably
我們大概
I thought
我自己想的
that is
就是說
Are we thinking that people are really that rational?
我們在想說人真的是那麼理性嗎
is when
就是當
You see everyone making up
你看到大家都在補
then you can't help
那你也沒有辦法
So you follow suit
所以你也跟著補
maybe you don't know
說不定你不知道
you look like
你看起來
you got a lot that day
你當天你得到不少東西
But what?
可是呢
half a year later
半年一年之後
you may have no income
你可能就沒有收入了
So we say people are so rational
所以我們說人是那麼理性的
If people only pay attention to this kind of short-term benefit
如果人只注重這一種短期的這一種利益
In fact, the interests of the whole society as a whole
其實對整個社會整體的利益
may be harmful
可能是會有傷害的
Ultimately for the long-term benefit of the individual
最後對個人的長遠利益
probably not too good
可能也不是太好的
so i just said
所以我剛剛講
that use of that common resource
那個公共資源的那一種使用
like this public fishing ground
像這個公共的這個漁場
this shit
不斷的這個爛補
In the long run, there are problems
其實長遠來講是有問題的
Then of course we will want to say
那再來我們當然會想說
that man is so independent
那人是那麼自立的
if people are so self-reliant
如果人那麼自立的話
Then why after communication and discussion
那為什麼經過溝通跟討論之後
Everyone is willing to give up this kind of short-term benefit
大家願意放棄短期的這一種利益
that considering the long-term
那考慮到長期的
This effort may lead to better
這個努力可能帶來更好的
The effect of individual and public
個人跟公共的那一種成效
That's a few questions I'm thinking about
那這是我想的幾個問題
So I also want to discuss here
所以我在這裡也想討論一下
Does that mean people are that rational?
就是說人有那麼的理性嗎
When we are talking about man being self-reliant
我們在談說人是自立的時候
Of course we would like to say that people want
當然我們會想說人要
able to calculate clearly
能夠很清楚的計算
Estimate how much you will pay
估算你付出的代價是多少
Then how much can you get
然後你能夠得到多少的成本
Is that man so rational?
那人有那麼理性嗎
that recently
那最近
last year
去年吧
Should be this
應該是這個
Professor of a business school at Duke University in the United States
美國的 Duke University 一個商學院的教授
he wrote a book called
他寫了一本書叫做
predictable irrationality
可預測的非理性
that book is quite interesting
那個書是相當有趣的
So I also read from that book
所以我也從那個書裡面
Take a few examples
摘取幾個例子
let's discuss
來跟大家討論一下
Are people that rational?
人有那麼的理性嗎
that person is not that rational
那人沒有那麼理性
what kind of problems will arise
會出現什麼樣的問題呢
we can think again
我們等一下可以再想一下
that first example
那第一個例子
i was going to say
我本來是想說
this speech is boring
這個演講太無聊
So please come with me on this
所以請大家跟我這個一起來
do some games
做一些遊戲
But because we are now
不過因為我們現在
Our classmate who took my class already knows
我們上過我的課的同學他已經知道了
So I dropped the idea
所以我就放棄了這個念頭了
That
那
What is this example?
這個是一個什麼例子呢
That means we now have zero 012 to 100
就是說我們現在有零012到100
012 to 100
012到100
Then you can try it
那各位可以試想一下
If we want to ask you now
我們現在如果要請各位
Please think of a number
要請各位你想一個數字
you have to think seriously
你要很認真的去想
write a number
寫一個數字
That means we're doing everyone writing a number
就是說我們在做每個人都寫一個數字
but
但是呢
our target is
我們的目標是
you wrote the right number
你寫對的這個數字
is close to the number written by everyone
是接近每一個人寫的這個數字的
2/3 of the average
平均值的3分之2
i say it again
我再講一次
Everyone understand what I mean
各位了解我講的這個意思
We now have this number from 0 to 100
我們現在有0到100的這個數字
You can write anywhere from 0 to 100
你可以隨便寫0到100
You can write 3 or 5
你寫3寫5都可以
but you have to notice
但是你要注意到
We want you to achieve this
我們希望各位達到的這個
what is the goal you want to achieve
就是你要達到的這個目標是什麼
you have to guess correctly
就你要正確的去猜對
Each of us fills in this number
我們每一個人填的這個數字
on average
平均起來
then multiply by 3 by 2
然後處以3乘以2
the value of
的那個數值
Although this is a small game
那這個雖然是一個小遊戲
But this is often spared
不過這個常常備用
Where is the backup?
在哪裡備用呢
about ten years ago
大概在十幾年前
There used to be a very boring person
這個就曾經有一個很無聊的人
On this plane flying from the UK to the US
在那個英國飛美國的這個飛機上面
this light exploded
這個燈爆
you are bored on the plane
就是你在飛機上無聊
You just give him a list like this
你就他給你這樣子的一個單子
tell you to write
叫你寫說
He'll send this list a thousand times
他會發這個單子發一千次
Then you can write in this grid on the plane
那在飛機上的這個成格都可以寫
His bonus is if you guessed right
他的這個獎金就如果你猜對了
the average
那個平均值的話
He is giving you one hundred thousand dollars
他是給你十萬塊美金
so this is high
所以這個是很高的
very high reward
很高的這個報酬
That's the first example ever brought up
那這是第一個曾經被提出來的例子
Then if you look at the online
那如果各位去看那個網路上的
the open course
那個開放式的這個課程
Michael Sandale, who is very popular recently
最近很紅的這個 Michael Sandale
speaking about justice
在講正義論
In fact, another very popular one is Yale University.
那其實另外一個很紅的是耶魯大學
There is also a game theory
還有一個叫做博弈理論
game theory
賽局理論
teacher first class
老師第一堂課
The homework for the students is this
也給學生的作業就是這個
Take out 10 U.S. dollars in class on the spot
當場在課堂上拿出10塊錢美金
Say send this list
說發下這個單子
If you write the closest to the average
你如果寫最接近平均值的
2.3 people who write averages per person
每個人寫的平均值的2.3人
Get a $10 bonus
就可以拿到10塊錢美金的獎金
There is also a well-known economist
還有一個很有名的經濟學家
at Caltech
在加州理工學院
He is also bold
他也是滿大膽的
his board of trustees at caltech
他在加州理工學院的董事會
I also made a game like this
也做了這樣子的一個遊戲
I also did it in class
我在上課的時候也做了
our class
我們這個上課
I'll show you the result
結果我先給大家看一下
Our National Taiwan University student
我們台大的這個學生
This student of National Taiwan University
台大的這個學生
Everyone fills in this number
每個人填的這個數字
We have more than 100 students
我們有100多個學生
The average is 39
平均數是39
20/3 of this average
這個平均數的3分之20
More than 100 students finally got this prize
100多個學生最後拿到這個獎品
It's the classmate who wrote 26
是寫26的這個同學
I just talked about the economists at Caltech
我剛講說加州理工學院的經濟學家
his board of trustees at caltech
他在加州理工學院的董事會
do the same thing
做同樣的事情
His average is 9
他的平均值是9
Game Theory at Yale University
在耶魯大學的賽局理論
The average in that class is 13
那個課裡面平均值是13
I'll start with the conclusion
那我先講結論
If a person is really that rational
如果一個人真的是那麼理性的
And he keeps on reasoning
而且他不斷的去推理的話
Logically speaking, if everyone is so rational
照理講如果所有人都這麼理性的話
That number should be 0
那個數字應該是0
should be 0
應該是0
then why let's see
那為什麼我們看一下
we have to have a hypothesis
我們要有一個假設
Everyone wants to maximize their own interests
每一個人都希望極大化自己的這個利益
That is to say, you must get
也就是說你一定要拿到
hope you get this prize
希望你拿到這個獎品
and you're assuming that other people are like you
那而且你假設別人跟你一樣
also the same
也是一樣
is perfectly rational
是完全理性的
Then you have to do this kind of repetitive
那你要進行這一種重複的
this rational analysis
這個理性的分析
then you can take a look
那你可以看一下
0 to 100
0到100
You can first think of
你可以第一個想法是
if it is random for everyone
如果它每個人是隨機的
its average is 33
它的平均數是33
So 2/3 is 22
所以3分之2就是22
right
對不對
this is an idea
這是一種想法
That assumes everyone has learned
那假設每個人都學過
what is this random assignment
這個隨機分配什麼
Then you figure it out to be 33
那你算出來是33
then you want
那你想
you know 33 you also assume each
你知道33你也假定每個
Others are as rational as you
其他人跟你一樣理性
right
對不對
So what is the value it calculates
所以它算出來的數值是多少
also 33
也是33
Well if everyone knows it's 33
那如果每個人都知道是33
you write 22
你寫22
Your chance to get this prize
你拿到這個獎品的這個機會
because everyone writes the same
因為每個人寫都一樣
so you're pushing down
所以你在往下推
then you know what to say
那你知道說
I'm thinking down
我在往下想
Everyone is equally rational
那每一個人都一樣理性
just write 22
就寫22
right
對不對
2/3 of 22
22的3分之2
you've been taking it off
你一直在把它除下去
Finally it becomes 0
最後就變成是0
right
對不對
but some people are smart
但是有一些人很聰明
need to know say
要知道說
Everyone is willing to spend so much time thinking about this question
每一個人都願意花那麼多時間想這個問題
So why did Caltech's board become long?
所以為什麼加州理工學董事會變成久呢?
He knows that some people don't think so much
他知道說有些人不會想那麼多
So he guessed that we should adjust it up
所以他就猜說我們就往上調一下
The one at Yanlu University is 13
那閻魯大學那個是13
Our Taiwan University students are more modest
我們臺大的同學比較謙虛一點
Yes 39 20
是39 20
So his average is 26
所以他的平均值是26
in this game
在這個遊戲裡面
If you fill in more than 67, it is completely irrational
你如果填67以上的是完全不理性的
right?
對不對?
Because two-thirds of the average
因為平均值的三分之二嘛
Suppose everyone writes 100
假設每一個人都寫100
That average is at least 67
那那個平均值至少67
Then you see if our classmates have written more than 67
那你看我們的同學有沒有寫超過67
Yes, there are still many
有啊還還不少啊
still twenty
還二十幾個
so you can understand
所以各位可以了解
That is to say, you have to conduct a rational analysis
就是說你要進行理性的分析
The first one is your ability
第一個你能力要夠
second you have enough time
第二個你要有足夠的時間
The third one you may have some knowledge
第三個你可能要有一些知識
Fourth, you may have to listen to the speech
第四個你可能要聽過演講
The fourth is my own
第四個是我自己家的
So this is the rational choice
所以這個是對於理性的這種選擇
Are we capable enough
我們是不是有那麼充分的能力
This issue is not very new
這個議題也不是很新的問題
not a new problem either
也不是很新的問題
Actually around the 1960s
其實大概在1960年代
another nobel
另外一個諾貝爾的
Economics or Psychology
應該是經濟學或是心理學
economics without psychology
經濟學沒有心理學
A professor of beauty in Karaji
在卡拉吉美人的一個教授
Called Herbert Simon mentioned that
叫 Herbert Simon 提到說
our bounded rationality
我們有限理性的
we are not so perfectly rational
我們不是那麼完全的理性
This is what we can see
這是我們可以看到
From this example it can be seen that
從這個例子裡面可以看到說
Human rationality is not as we imagined
人的理性不是像我們想像的
so perfect
那麼的完美的
Then we just mentioned
那我們剛剛提到說
short term benefit
短期的這個利益
with long-term benefits
跟長期的這個利益
What is the relationship between
這中間的關係到底是什麼
is whether we will
就是我們會不會願意
for the long-term benefit
為了長期的這個利益
at the expense of this short-term benefit
而犧牲了這個短期的這個利益
Then when Arie is what I just said
那這個當Arie就是我剛剛講
write predictable this irrational this academic
寫可預測的這個不理性的這個學者
He said most of us
他說我們大部分人
see short-term benefits
看到短期的利益
we usually enjoy it right away
我們通常會立刻享用
long time we will wait
長期的我們就等等
This can't wait that long anyway
這個反正也等不了那麼久
then he made a
那他就做了一個
did a this this this research
做了一個這個這個這個研究
This research seems to be very simple
這個研究看起來也是非常簡單
very simple
非常簡單
Well, this is actually in the school
那這個其實在學校裡面
We often encounter
我們常常大概會碰到
Then he will be divided into three groups
那他就分成三組
ABC three groups
ABC三組
The first group is to submit three reports together at the end of the term
第一組是期末一起交三份報告
That's only twelve weeks
那這個一共只有十二週
This is the word of the Quote
這個是這個Quote字的
The second group is the teacher's rule
那第二組是老師規定
fourth week second week
第四週第二週
In the eighth week and the twelfth week, you must teach the report you want to teach
第八週、第十二週,你必須要把你要教的報告教出來
The third group is set by the students themselves to teach the time of three feet
第三組是由學生自己設定三個腳教的時間
But as long as you teach, you will deduct 1% of the points for every day you teach
但是你只要持教,每持教一天你就扣1%的分數
So we now have three groups
所以我們現在有三組
This is the third group, and the students set the time for teaching three feet
這個是第三組,由學生自己設定三個腳教的時間
Commitment to teach the first point and report the second point when
承諾在什麼時候教第一分、報告第二分
It can be from the first week to the tenth week
就是第一週到第十週都可以
You have complete freedom to set the time you want to teach the presentation
你有完全的自由度來設定你要教報告的時間
Then he took three classes, and the places where he did his research were all in these prestigious schools in the Ivy League
那他找了三個班,他做的研究的地方都是在長春藤的這些名校
Harvard Yale places
哈佛耶魯這些地方
The performance of the whole school, V is the best
那整個學業的表現,V是最好的
What is V?
V是什麼呢?
prescribed by the teacher
由老師規定
When was it handed in?
什麼時候交的?
And then? What comes next?
然後呢?其次是什麼?
followed by C
其次是 C
It is when the students themselves promise to hand in
就是學生自己承諾在什麼時候交的
What about the worst?
那最糟糕的呢?
The worst is A
最糟糕的是 A
Submit a three-point report at the end of the term
期末一起交三分報告
So why is it such a bad idea to hand in three-point reports together at the end of the term?
那為什麼期末一起交三分報告會很糟糕呢?
because of the report
因為要交報告
Anyway, twelve weeks later.
反正是十二週以後的事情
So there is a community in the middle
所以中間有社團啊
what are you going to do
要去幹嘛啦
I want to help people run for election.
要幫人家競選啊
Or go to work, wait
或者去打工啊等等
Anyway, let's play first.
反正先玩了再說啦
he is dying
他死到臨頭
Let's hold Buddha's feet together, this us
在一起來抱佛腳這個我們
very simple
很簡單
all know
都知道
That
那
it's interesting
這有趣的是
looks like
看起來
It seems that even in the US
看起來即使是在美國
even in the US
即使是在美國
Even though there may be teacher rules in the U.S.
即使在美國可能有老師規定呢
The situation he behaved
他表現的這個情況
will be the best
會是最好的
But you have to pay attention to one thing
不過各位要注意一件事情
he carefully analyzed
他仔細地去分析
to analyze carefully
仔細地去分析
That is to say, there are students who promise to hand in
就是說有學生自己承諾要交的
Although his achievement is in the middle
雖然他的這個成就是在中間
but a very interesting thing
不過非常有趣的一件事情
If the promise he wrote himself is delivered to someone who can do it
如果他自己寫的承諾要交的做得到的人
Actually he's doing very well
其實他的表現都非常好
Why does C get worse?
C為什麼會變差呢
It's because these braggarts said when they would hand in
是因為這些吹牛自己說要什麼時候交
but not on time
但是沒有準時交
As a result, the results of the C group are pulled down
結果把C這個群組的成績往下拉
Otherwise he wouldn't have performed no worse than an A
否則的話他的表現不會不亞於A
No less than B No less than B No less than the teacher stipulated
不亞於B不亞於B不亞於老師規定的
I don't want to give you a false impression about this research.
這個研究我不想給各位一個錯覺
Because the teacher may represent the country or the government
因為老師代表的可能就是國家代表是政府
We just want an authoritarian dictatorship to set what time
我們只要威權統治獨裁政府設定什麼時間
It tells you that you must complete the efficiency and the result will be the best.
叫你必定完成那效率成果會最好
Academic performance will be the best
學業表現會最好
So one cylinder is the best
所以一缸一本最好
right
對不對
that or
那或者是
stop here
就講到這裡
So this self-sufficiency
所以這個自給自治
if autonomy is possible
如果自治能夠做得到的話
In fact, his results are not too bad.
其實他的這個成果都不會太差
The point is that there will always be a minority
關鍵在於其實永遠有少數的人
There are a few people he can't help
有少數的人他沒有辦法
For what's going to happen twelve weeks from now
對於長遠十二週以後要發生的事情
His blood score is actually very important to him.
這個他的血液成績其實對他是非常重要的
But at the moment his interests
可是當下他的利益
What are you doing playing?
玩一玩幹什麼
or just go and listen to a professor speak
或隨便去聽某個教授演講
If I tell you to go back and prepare for the midterm exam, you don't want it.
叫你回去準備期中考你就不要
like help
像助不此類的
Then this will affect your preparation for this class
那這個會影響你的這個課業的這種準備
But once you are autonomous
但是一旦你是能夠自治的
Although this C is between B and C
這個 C 雖然在 B 跟 C 中間
In fact, his effect is also good.
其實他的這個效果也是不錯的
So if we want to be able to overcome this short-term benefit
所以我們如果要能夠克服短期的這一種利益
Then do some regulation on your own initiative
那自己自動自發的做一些規範
So if you release it, in fact it can still be solved
所以釋放的話,事實上它還是可以解決
can still solve the problem of delay
還是可以解決這種拖延的問題
for the long-term benefit
還是可以對於長期的這一種利益
It's this effect to complete
它的這個成效去完成
So this is the second experiment
所以這個是第二個實驗
The third experiment was
第三個實驗是
Let's go back to the fundamental question
我們還是再回到根本的問題
Are people so rational?
人是不是那麼的理性
This is the third experiment is will you cheat
這是第三個實驗是你會不會作弊
Anyway, he thinks about these things every day
反正他每天在想這些有的沒有的
these studies
這些研究
I just told you where he did the research
我剛講說他做這個研究的地點
At Harvard, MIT, Yale, Britston, UZL
在哈佛、MIT、耶魯、Britston、UZL
these schools
這幾個學校
he has 50 questions
他有50個問題
10 cents for each correct answer
每答對一題給10分錢
10 cents per catty
每斤給10分錢
he has four groups
他有四組
He is the first to issue an answer ticket
他是先發一個答案券
Send out the topic, the booklet first, and send out a copy of this booklet first
先發題目、題本、先發一本這個題本
You write the answer on the question book
這個題本你就在題本上面寫答案
About 40 minutes after writing the answer
寫完答案之後大概經過40分鐘
40 minutes until you finish writing
40分鐘等你寫完了
He is sending you an answer card to fill in with 2B pliers
他在發一個要用2B鉗筆去填的答案卡給你
I want you to lift it up
要你把它騰上去
This control group is after you fill out the answer card
這個控制組就是你填完答案卡之後
by the teacher
由老師來改
in this case
在這個情況底下
52 questions total average
52題一共平均
Average 32.6 correct answers
平均答對了32.6
32.6
32.6
So it means that he can get more than 3 dollars
所以就表示說他能夠拿到3塊多美金
There are not many reporters
這個報長也不是很多
not many
也不是很多
What about the second group?
那第二組呢
What about the second group and the first group?
第二組跟第一組呢
After he handed out the answer card himself
他就是自己發答案卡之後
After sending out the answer card for you to fill out
發要你填的答案卡之後
give you the correct answer
再給你正確答案
you go right
你自己去對
How many questions did you get right?
結果對了幾題呢
36.2
36.2
Of course he's sure
那當然他很確定的
Group 1234 basically has the same knowledge and abilities
1234組基本上他的知識能力什麼都一樣
And he did look at this answer card of his
而且他的確有去看他的這個答案卡
Does his answer card have the trace of the picture modification?
他的答案卡有沒有那個圖改的這個痕跡
He can know with certainty that
他可以很確定的知道說
This 4.2 is cheating
這個4.2是作弊
The result after changing the graph
圖改之後造成的這個結果
the third one
那第三個
The third one is also the answer
第三個也是自己對答案
And what makes it even harder for you to track is
而更讓你沒有辦法去追蹤的就是
He took the topic paper
他把那個題目紙
you can put it in a sleeping paper machine
你可以放在睡紙機裡面
you destroy it
你把它消毀掉
But your answer card is still reserved for this host of that study.
但是你答案卡還是留給那個研究的這個主持人
The fourth group is
那第四組是
How much does it cost? Anyway, you take it yourself, it doesn't matter
連要多少錢呢?反正你自己拿啦,沒有關係啦
This is completely unrestricted, then you have to find out
這個完全沒有約束,那你要發現
From the second group, the third group, and the fourth group, in fact, it correctly answers the difference in this question
從第二組、第三組、第四組,其實它答對著這個題目的差別
There is not much difference in this
沒有太大的這個差異
So this is very surprising, why?
那這個令人非常訝異,為什麼?
Very surprised, that is to say, when we are speculating, when we are cheating
非常訝異,就是說我們在投機、我們在作弊的時候
We're not going to calculate the cost of getting caught
我們不會去仔細計算被逮到的這個成本
Why do you say that about the relationship with the benefits you get?
跟你得到的這個利益的關係,為什麼這麼說呢?
Like this you answer the answer yourself, but the one written above your title
像這個你自己對答案,但是你的題目上面寫的那個
The answers written on the question paper are the same as those on the answer coupon.
題目紙上面寫的答案跟答案券上面的
Our researchers are right about this, then this
這個我們研究者是可以對的,那這個
By the time of the fourth group, there is almost no evidence
到第四組的時候幾乎是沒有什麼任何證據了
No one knows you, it's not that no one knows
也沒有人知道你到底,不是說沒有人知道
Can't find it out, there's nothing in the whole
查不出來,整體全都沒有
How is the whole class?
全班之道整個情況是怎麼樣
But there is no way to identify individuals
可是沒有辦法指認個人
Logically speaking, it's impossible to get caught like this.
照理說像這個是完全不會被抓到的
you can brag
你可以吹牛說
You just straight out of this jar
你就直接從這個罐子裡面
take four or five bucks
把四塊或五塊錢拿走
means you got it right
表示你答對的
This kind of reward to you later
之後的給你的這種報酬
we will not calculate
我們不會去計算
look
你看
This one has the highest risk of getting caught
這個被抓到的風險最高
this minimum
這個最低
But the way we behave
可是我們表現出來的行為的方式
one time
是一次的
have you been caught
有沒有被抓
when you want to cheat
當你想要作弊的時候
when there is an opportunity to cheat
有機會作弊的時候
risk of getting caught
被抓到的風險
you're not thinking
你考慮的並不是
not
並不是
than the cost-benefit relationship between the
比這之間的成本效益的關係
you don't think so much
你不會去想那麼多
in this experiment
在這個實驗裡面
We can see that
我們可以看到
That is to say, if ethics and norms
就是說如果道德跟規範
when not so mandatory
沒有那麼強制的時候
That man has this head muscle
那人是有這個頭肌
There is a tendency to speculate
是有投機的這個傾向
so we say dishonest
所以我們說不誠實
Of course he destroys
當然他主義破壞
This transaction in the entire market
這整個市場的這種交易
Same time as Osha
跟歐紗同一個時間
williamson won the nobel prize in economics
拿到諾貝爾經濟學獎的威廉森
He mentioned that this opportunism
他提到說這個投機主義
is to invalidate the market
是讓這個市場失效
quite an important factor
相當重要的一個因素
market failure
市場失效
At the level of the human actor there are two
在人的行動者這個層次有兩個
bounded rationality
一個是有限理性
one is opportunism
一個是投機主義
will make this market impossible to operate
會讓這個市場沒有辦法運作
that's dishonest
那不誠實
he can also destroy
他也可以破壞
The sense of trust in the entire community members
這整個社區成員裡面的信任感
No one wants to follow this norm
沒有人願意遵守這個規範
what i mean is
那我的意思就是說
actually dishonest
其實不誠實
lack of trust
缺乏信任
Not only the operation of the market is no way
不僅市場的運作是沒有辦法
what i mentioned
我所提到的
That is to say, it is developed spontaneously by actors
就是說由行動者自動自發所發展出來的
the system that governs that public good
治理那種公共財的那個制度
he can't help
他也沒有辦法
also does not work
也沒有辦法運作
In this example inside
在這個例子裡面
all i want to say is to say
我想要說的就是說
In fact, people are not so
人事實上沒有那麼的
as rational as we imagined
像我們想像中的那麼的理性
So if we're not that rational
所以如果我們沒有那麼理性的話
In this uncertain environment
在不確定的這個環境底下
We just saw that we have no way to calculate
我們剛剛看到我們沒有辦法計算
when
什麼時候
how to when
怎麼樣達到什麼時候
can maximize their own interests
可以極大化自己的這個利益
The second experiment is to say
第二個實驗是說
We'll see short-term benefits of this
我們會看到短期的這個利益
we are priority
我們是優先考慮
but we often forget
但是我們常常忘了
There are long-term benefits of this
有長期的這種利益
The third is this rational ability
第三個是這種理性的這個能力
if not so full
如果不是那麼充分的話
then he might be involved in this
那他可能牽涉到這個
this stage of this development of morality
道德的這種發展的這個階段
no way to go any further
沒有辦法再往前進展
that is
就是說
your code of ethics
你的這個道德的這個規範
the ability to abide by the code of ethics
遵守這個道德規範的這個能力
not so solid
不是那麼的穩固
not so stable
不是那麼的穩定
That
那
he has the potential to cause opportunism
他有可能造成投機主義
So what I'm actually trying to say here is to say
所以我在這裡其實想要說的就是說
Reason of course it is for intelligence
理性當然它是對於智力
is a very important element
是非常重要的一個元素
but I think it's necessary
但是我認為它是必要條件
it is not a sufficient condition
它不是充分條件
That reason it is for this morality this development
那理性它對於這種道德這個發展
In fact it is very important
事實上也是非常關鍵的
And this psychologist in Switzerland
那這個在瑞士的心理學家
Peter J.
Pierre J.
And then this one from Harvard University
然後後來哈佛大學的這個
The professor of psychology
心理學的這個教授
Kopach he referred to this moral development
Kopach他提到這個道德發展的
different stage
不同的這個階段
In fact, based on the development of morality
其實建立在道德這個發展
must also be built on
也必須要建立在
this rational faculty
這個理性的能力上面
Then this ability is insufficient
那這個能力不足
How to do it
怎麼辦呢
What to do if the ability is insufficient
能力不足怎麼辦
What about lack of rational ability?
理性能力不足怎麼辦呢
Then we can only see if there is a more rational
那我們只能想看有沒有更為理性的
this way
這一種辦法
then we just mentioned
那我們剛剛提到
That is to say, a public discussion in a community
就是說一個社群的公共討論
things i know
我知道的東西
i may have some limitations
我可能有一些限制
Then I can discuss with other people
然後我可以跟其他人一起討論
It might be possible to develop a more rational
那可能可以發展出更為理性的這一種
This mechanism of supervision and punishment
監督懲罰的這個機制
like this fishing village in this alenya in Türkiye
就像在土耳其的這個阿倫亞的這個漁村
Or that we develop a more pronounced morality
或者是說我們發展出更明顯的這一種道德
Or this kind of constraint of the specification
或者是規範的這一種約束
that would make our kind of bounded rationality
那可以使得我們這一種有限理性
The problem with opportunism
跟投機主義的這個問題
can get some restrictions
可以得到一些限制
As for this change in behavioral theory
那至於行為理論的這個改變
I will not talk for now
我就先暫時不講
skip it first
先把它跳過去
This is because there is not enough time
這個因為有一點時間不是那麼足夠
I just mentioned that
那我剛剛提到就是說
This study from Ostron
從Ostron的這個研究
Whether people are so rational is a question
人是不是那麼理性這是一個問題
The second question is
那第二個問題就是說
Is that man like we said
那人是不是像我們所說的
so selfish
那麼的這個自私
So I'm giving two different messages here
那我在這裡提供兩個不同的訊息
One is an anthropologist and this economist
一個是人類學家跟這個經濟學家
This study in the Garden Out Society
在園出社會的這個研究
The other one is social members of different age groups
那另外一個是不同年齡層的社會成員
Comparison among different indigenous societies
在不同原住社會的比較
I mostly based it on the book
我主要是根據這本書
It was published by Oxford University in 2003
這是牛津大學在2003年出版的
It is the study of the social basis of human beings
就是人的這種社會性基礎的研究
What about his research?
那他的這個研究呢
you can see this cover
你可以看到這個封面
He is in 15 indigenous communities
他是在15個原住社
probably in the past ten years
大概是在過去十幾年
where are they
他們呢
they are at this age
他們在這個年齡
over the past ten years they
他們在過去十幾年
where are they
他們呢
economist psychologist
經濟學家心理學家
combined with anthropologists
結合了人類學家
to do this research
去做的這個研究
The location of this study
那這個研究的這個地點
What about the research site?
研究的這個地點呢
from africa
從非洲
Then to this Indonesia
然後到這個印尼
Then
然後
New Guinea
新幾內亞
then to this
然後到這個
latin america
拉丁美洲
latin america is in bolivia
拉丁美洲是在波利維亞
then bolivia
然後波利維亞
Peru and Ecuador
密魯還有俄瓜多
these places
這些地方
I think this book is quite interesting
這本書我是覺得還蠻有意思的
because we can see the differences between different societies
因為我們可以看到不同的社會之間的差異
In fact, they want to do this kind of research in this kind of primitive tribe
其實他們要在這種原初部落做這樣的研究
It will probably take two or three years
大概都要花個兩三年的時間
But they are taking the same data collection method
但他們是採取同樣的資料收集的方式
Why do they cooperate with economists in the collection of data
他們資料的收集為什麼要跟經濟學家合作
Because they mainly use this game
因為他們主要是用這個遊戲
game of economic resource allocation
經濟資源分配的遊戲來進行的
This is of course more difficult
這個當然是比較困難的
They mainly have three different ways of playing
他們主要大概有三個不同的遊戲的方式
This relates to what I'm going to talk about later.
這個牽涉到我等一下要講的內容
The first game called Dictator
第一個叫做獨裁者的遊戲
The dictator's game is me as the allocator of resources
獨裁者的遊戲就是我當成資源的分配者
If I have a hundred dollars in my hand
我手上如果有一百塊的話
I can assign to this gentleman
我可以分配給這位先生
I can totally decide how much money I want to allocate to him
我可以完全決定我要分配給他多少錢
i am a dictator
我是獨裁者
I have a hundred yuan, and I can allocate as much as you want
我有一百塊,我分配給你多少就多少
if i was completely self-reliant
如果我是完全自立的話
i'm a dictator now i have a hundred dollars
我現在是獨裁者,我手上有一百塊
how much do you think i will give him
那你認為我會分給他多少錢
How much? Not even a dime
多少?一毛錢都不給啊
so i can stand on my own
這樣我才自立嘛
Otherwise, it would be wrong for me to give him a dollar.
不然我要給他一塊錢就不對啦
I'm a dictator, he can't do anything to me
我是獨裁者,他又不能對我怎麼樣
Right? What missiles do I have? What planes do I have?
對不對?我有什麼飛彈啊?我有什麼飛機啊?
that can't do anything to me ? he has nothing
那不能把我怎麼樣啊?他什麼都沒有
This is the first dictator of this game
這是第一個獨裁者的這個遊戲
What about the second one?
第二個呢
The second game of his is the game of ultimatum
第二個他的這個遊戲是最後通諜的這個遊戲
the game is the same
那這個遊戲是一樣的
i have a hundred dollars
我有一百塊
Then I decide how much to allocate to him
那我決定分配給他多少錢
but he has a
但是他有一個
Unlike the dictator just now
跟剛剛獨裁者不一樣的
So decide to accept or not
所以決定接受或不接受
Suppose I have one hundred yuan, I give him twenty, and I keep eighty for myself
假設我有一百塊,我給他二十,我自己留八十
if he decides not to accept
他如果決定不接受的話
Please be aware of this
請各位注意這一點
we two have nothing
我們兩個一無所有
Do you understand?
各位了解嗎?
That is, I have a hundred dollars and give him twenty dollars
就是我有一百塊分給他二十塊
The ultimatum is here
最後通諜就在這裡
That's how I divide resources now
就是我現在資源就分這樣了
Then you have to decide whether you accept it or not
那你要決定了你到底接不接受
The condition I put forward
我提出的這個條件
I keep eighty, you take twenty
我留八十,你拿二十塊
if you don't agree
那你如果不同意的話
you won't get a dime
你一毛錢拿不到
I can't get a dime
我一毛錢也拿不到
So this is the game of ultimatum
所以這是最後通諜的這個遊戲
let's see
那我們看一下
They are in these fifteen different circles out of society
他們在這十五個不同的這個圓出社會
They all used something like this
他們都用了像這個
This is the game of ultimatum
這個是最後通諜的這個遊戲
The game of ultimatum
最後通諜的這個遊戲
Then you can see in these sixteen
那你可以看到在這十六個
fifteen different places
十五個不同的地方
There is a P word treasure interspersed in the middle
中間穿插了一個P字寶
This is America's P
這是美國的P字寶
0.5 means you spend the money you have
0.5就是你把你手上有的錢
researchers give you money
研究者給你的錢
You give half to each other
你分一半給對方
divide the circle
分這個圓圈
The size of the circle in the middle represents
中間這個圓圈的大小代表
The members of the study who participated in the test
受試的參加這個研究的成員
He gives half to the other party
他分一半給對方的比例
The size of the ratio that allocates half to the other party
分配一半給對方的比例的大小
So guys in this chart you can see
所以各位在這個圖表裡面你可以看到
you can see
你可以看到
This P word treasure in the United States
美國的這個P字寶
About half of the study participants
研究的參與者大概有差不多一半的人
if he gets 100
如果他拿到100塊
in the ultimatum game
在最後通牒的遊戲裡面
he will assign to each other
他會分配給對方
about 50 yuan
大概50塊錢
Usually the chances of being rejected in this case are not high
通常在這情況底下被拒絕的可能性不高
look at the bottom
你看一下最底下的
These two places are in Miru
這兩個地方這個是在蜜魯
This one is in Milu, and this one is in Erhuadu
這個在蜜魯,這個在二花多
You can take a look at this in Miru
各位可以看一下在蜜魯這個
What is the most people give it?
它最多人給的是多少?
15%
15%
That is 100 yuan, it gives 15 yuan to the other party
就是100塊它給對方15塊
And surprisingly, 85 yuan
而令人非常驚訝的是85塊
That is 100 yuan, you give the other party 15 yuan and you keep 85 yuan
就是100塊你給對方15塊你留85塊
Here its rejection is very very low
在這裡它拒絕力是非常非常低的
very very low
非常非常低的
Then this is somewhat different from our general understanding.
那這跟我們一般的這個理解會有一些差別
Basically speaking, the original society
這一些原出的這個社會基本上來講
They can be said to be a cooperative economy
他們可以說是一個合作經濟
Like P word treasure, of course it is a kind of capitalism
像P字寶這個當然是一個資本主義的這一種
the shape of the economy
經濟的這個形態
a lot of competition
非常多的競爭
then emphasize personal interests
然後強調個人的利益
right
對不對
then in this case
那在這種情況底下
why would he
為什麼他會
Everyone give 50
大家都給50呢
Give the other party 50 out of 100 yuan
100塊裡面給對方50
Instead, what we see
反而在我們看到的這些
the following
下面這些
The entire 15 tribes
這整個15個部落
Distinguished in various parts of the world
分辨在全世界各個地方
he is a food
他是一個食物啦
hit this hand cracked thing
打到這手裂得到的東西
must be shared
都必須要分享的
This original society
這個原出的這個社會
Relatively speaking
相對來講
them
他們
provide to
提供給
Others
他族人
or this member of his tribe
或他部落裡面的這個成員
What about the resources given to him?
給他的這個資源呢
Relatively speaking
相對來說
not what we imagined
並沒有我們想像的
so many
那麼的多
not as much as we thought
並沒有我們想像的那麼多
then we are here
那我們在這裡
I'm here
我在這裡
he
他
don't explain too much about this
不做太多的這個解釋
because this
因為這個
is quite complicated
是蠻複雜的
quite complicated
蠻複雜的
I just talk
我只講說
50% on this P-SYB
在這個 P-SYB 百分之 50%
This involves the receiver
這個牽涉到接受者
one of his thoughts on fairness
他對於公平的一個想法
That is to say
也就是說
In a society like America
在像美國這樣子的一個社會
most people would think
大部分人會認為
what is a fair
什麼是一個公平的
This way of resource allocation
這種資源分配的方式
It's everyone's half and half
就是大家對半盆
that in this ultimatum game
那在這個最後通牒遊戲裡面
who you want to allocate resources to
你要分配資源的人
you must think of one thing
你一定會想到一件事情
If I allocate this resource
如果我在分配這個資源的時候
I don't take into account the other person's feelings and thoughts
我不考慮到對方的感受跟想法
we may not get both
我們兩個可能都拿不到
so what
所以呢
Your best bet is you don't get rejected
你最好的辦法是你不要被拒絕
if you understand each other
如果你理解對方
acceptable
能夠接受的
think this is a fair distribution
認為公平分配的這個
If this ratio is 50%
這個比例是百分之 50%的話
your best way
你最好的辦法
You are 50%
你就是分百分之 50%
to each other
給對方
Only in this way can you get this resource
那這樣子的話你才有可能拿到這個資源
in other societies
那在其他的這一些社會
like this one in indonesia
像這個是在印尼
Then this is more than what Pizibao offers
那這比皮子堡更提供的這個
that's it you can see
就是它你可以看到
It's up to 50%
它最多的是50%
But most of them are more than 50%
可是它大多數是超過50%
most are over 50%
大多數是超過50%
What kind of society is this?
那這個是一個什麼樣的社會呢
It is the first goldfish specifically listed in the Indonesian sea
它是在印尼海邊專門首列這個金魚
Dedicated to the first goldfish
專門首列這個金魚
Then you know how to shoot a big goldfish
那你知道要打一條大的這個金魚
It may have to be forty or fifty people together
它可能是必須要四五十個人一起
Together
一起
Very detailed and precise division of labor
很詳細很精密的這個分工
so in this place
所以在這個地方
What kind of communication among group members do they
他們對於那一種團體成員之間的
this social bond
這個社會連帶
and the one who shared
還有分享的那個
specification can say
規範可以說
is the ultimate state
是達到極致的狀態
So he would rather give the other party a little more
所以他寧願給對方多一點
I would rather give each other more
寧願給對方多一點
so this is very special
所以這是非常特別的
the other i'm here
那其他的我在這邊
I won't explain too much
我不再做太多的說明
But the point here is to say
不過這邊要講的就是說
inside a community
一個社區裡面
within a community
一個社群裡面
He developed it because of his lifestyle
他因為生活方式所發展出來的
that norm and value
那一種規範跟價值
in fact affects
事實上會影響到
He is in this game of economic resource allocation
他在這個經濟資源分配的遊戲裡面
how does he do the distribution
他怎麼樣做分配的方式
You can see this chart more clearly
這個圖表各位可以看得更清楚
It can be seen more clearly that
可以看得更清楚就是
We just talked about this in Indonesia
我們剛剛講印尼的這個
He's in this game of ultimatum
他在最後通牒的這個遊戲
he gave the most
他給的是最多的
What about this one?
那這一張呢
this one
這一張
This one is the game of the dictator
這一張是獨裁者的這個遊戲
That is to say
也就是說
i have a hundred dollars
我有一百塊
how much for you
給你多少錢
There is no way for the other party to refuse
對方是沒有辦法拒絕的
So in this dictator's game
所以在這個獨裁者的遊戲裡面
He will clearly show up saying
他會很清楚地顯現出來說
Are we so Chilean
我們是不是那麼的智利
You can take a look
各位可以看一下
This is an American worker
這個是美國的工人
Then this black one is
然後這個黑色的是
Is the Iraqi immigrants to the United States
就是伊拉克裔的移民到美國
And then they have a small community of this
然後他們有一個小型的這個社區
that in this gray
那在這個灰色的
The gray one is a college student
灰色的這個是大學生
this is a college student
這個是大學生
Then you can see that
那各位可以看到就是說
in the middle
在這中間
this is you have 100
這是你有100塊
You give the other party 50 yuan
你分50塊給對方
That's what we just talked about in the Dictator game
那在獨裁者遊戲我們剛才已經講過了
you have 100 yuan
你有100塊
You shouldn't give each other a dime
你一毛錢都不應該分給對方
you are chile
你才是智利
right
對不對
So you see this worker in America
那所以你看到美國的這個工人
This worker in the United States does not have nearly a million
美國的這個工人他沒有將近百萬
70% when he has 100
70% 當他有100塊的時候
He will give the other party 50 yuan
他會分 50 塊給對方
His percentage is higher in minority communities
少數族裔的社區他的比例更高了
Nearly 80
將近 80 幾
Transnational Studies in Dictator's Game
在獨裁者的遊戲跨國的研究
usually no one
通常大概沒有人
Few studies were seen across different countries
幾乎沒有看到跨不同國家的研究
I didn't see that someone said that they didn't share with each other at all.
沒有看到說有人完全不分給對方
At least 20% more to 40%
至少都 20% 多的到 40%
20% to 40% in the middle
20% 到 40% 這個中間
So we can compare from different groups
所以我們可以從不同群體之間的比較
We can see that
我們可以看到
In fact, people are not as selfish as we think
其實人沒有像我們想像中的那麼的自私
But of course some people are very selfish
但是當然有些人是非常自私的
not a dime
一毛錢不給的
wait a minute we'll talk about a question
等一下我們會談到一個問題
Of course some people are altruistic if they are not selfish
當然有些人不自私是利他的
some people are selfish
有些人是自私人
what happens when they are together
他們一起的時候會發生什麼事情
we'll see later
我們等一下再看
Let's look at the different age groups
我們先看看不同年齡層的
I just talked about different societies
剛剛講的是不同社會的
This comparison of members of different age groups
不同年齡層的成員的這個比較
This is 7 years old and 10 years old
這個是7歲 10歲
11 years old 13 years old 17 years old
11歲 13歲 17歲
This one is female
這一條這個是女性
this is male
這個是男性
you can see
各位可以看到
This is from 20 coins you have
這是從你有的20個硬幣
this is hero
這個是英棒
that's 20 coins
就是20個硬幣
How much do you give each other
你分多少個給對方
that's a dictator
那是獨裁者
You can see this 7-year-old kid
各位可以看到7歲的這個小孩
he has 20 coins
他有20個硬幣
He will probably give the opponent an average
他大概平均會分給對方
then the trend
然後這個趨勢
this girl
這個女生
to 17 years old
到17歲
Nothing much has changed with this
沒有什麼太大的這個改變
good
好
if you look at boys
那如果你看男生的話
Compare
比較
Probably in all studies probably have this
大概在所有的研究大概都有這個
relatively consistent conclusion
比較一致的結論
Boys usually give less to each other
男生通常分給對方的會比較少
will be less
會比較少
This is on research
這個是在研究上面
probably very clear
大概是很清楚的
a phenomenon
一個現象
so you can watch
所以你可以看
Our little friend who was about seven years old
我們大概在七歲的這個小朋友
He won't be what we imagined
他不會那麼像我們想像中的
then this intelligence
那麼的這個智力
not so intelligent
不會那麼的這個智力
Okay, let's see this in Taiwan
好 那這個我們看看在台灣
This is our latest
這個是我們最近
In Penghu and in New Taipei City
在澎湖跟在新北市
the research done
所做的這個研究
i should be faster
我應該要快一點
so what
所以呢
I give everyone
我給大家
I'll just talk about this
我就講這個
This is fifth grade
這個是五年級
this is seventh grade
這個是七年級
This is the eleventh grade
這個是十一年級
Then let me tell you, please pay attention
那我講各位請注意看
I'll talk about this row first
我先講這一排
it's a dictator's game
這是獨裁者的遊戲
That is to say, this kid has 30 yuan in his hand
就是說這個小朋友手上有30塊
This is five years old, seven years old, eleven years old
這是五歲、七歲、十一歲
No, fifth grade, seventh grade, eleventh grade
不,五年級、七年級、十一年級的
It distributes the 30 yuan to the other party
它這個30塊裡面分配給對方
Our sample adds up to
我們這個樣本總加起來
There are about 400 students
大概有400多個學生
Each grade has about 100
每一個年級大概有100多個
More than 100 or so
100多個左右
You can take a look
各位可以看一下
Our kid in fifth grade
我們五年級的這個小朋友
It is assigned to each other with an average of 18.6
它分配給對方的是平均是18.6
That is to say it will be nearly more than half
也就是說它將近超過一半
Then the seventh grade is about 17.0
然後七年級的大概是17.0
Then the eleventh grade
然後這個十一年級
The student in the second year of high school is about 16.3
就高二的這個學生大概16.3
So that compared to
所以那個相較之下
This student of ours is assigning this resource
我們的這個學生在分配這個資源
when giving to each other
給對方的時候
this time for the other party
給對方的這個時候
He is quite generous
他給的算是蠻慷慨的
Not as Chilean as we thought
沒有像我們想像中的那麽智利
Then we just mentioned that
那我們剛剛提到就是說
from different tribes
從不同的部落
A Comparison of Different Original Owner Societies
不同的原主社會的比較
Then to this kid of different ages
然後到不同年齡層的這個小朋友
We can see that any one
我們可以看到隨便找一個
we will see something like
我們會看到像
Even with this college student in the United States
即使以美國的這個大學生
Some people are more Chilean
有些人是比較智利的
what about some people
那有些人呢
he is generous or fair
他是很慷慨的或公平的
treat others
對待別人的
So we are in a society
所以我們在一個社會裡面
we are in a society
我們在一個社會裡面
We are actually Chilean individuals
我們其實是智利的個人
the altruistic other
跟利他主義的這個他人
he is in a community
他在一個社群裡面
he will have some interaction
他是會有一些互動的
have some contacts
有一些往來的
that was in 2003
那這是在2003年
Some scholars in this Switzerland
這個瑞士的一些學者
the research they did
他們所做的這個研究
What is their research doing
他們的這個研究做的是什麼
What you do is to say that in a game of public wealth
做的就是說在一個公共財的遊戲裡面
Let's see how everyone paid at the beginning
那看看開始的時候大家怎麼付出
Then let this game of public wealth
然後讓這個公共財的這個遊戲
Continue to operate ten times, twenty times
不斷地去操作進行個十次、二十次
The game of public goods is
公共財的這個遊戲是
Each of us has hands on hands Let's say we now have five people
我們手上每個人手上假設我們現在有五個人
Each of us has 100 yuan
我們每個人手上有100塊
Then our 100 yuan
那我們這100塊
If I take out this 100 yuan
如果我把這個100塊拿出來
It's up to you to decide how much you want to spend out of 100 yuan
100塊裡面看你決定你要拿多少錢出來
5 or 10
5塊或10塊
after taking it out
拿出來之後
It becomes this resource in a public
它就變成是在一個公共的這個資源
Then this researcher will multiply by three times
那這個研究者他會乘以三倍
if i take 5 dollars out
如果我拿5塊錢出來
triple
乘以三倍
The three lists are 15
這三個單子是15
Multiplied by 15 and then scored for the five people participating in the public money game
乘以15之後再評分給參加公共財遊戲的這五個人
So a person can get three dollars
所以一個人可以拿到三塊錢
Fully self-reliant people in this public money game
在這個公共財遊戲裡面完全自立的人
He doesn't have to take out a dime
他一毛錢都不用拿出來
but he just has to wait
但是他只要等著
After someone else took out the money and tripled it
有別人把錢拿出來乘以三倍之後
Naturally he can distribute the benefits
他自然而然可以分配得到好處
Get benefits
得到利益
In this public money game
在這個公共財遊戲
You can see that at the beginning
你可以看到一開始的時候
what everyone is willing to pay
大家願意付出的
there are many people willing to give
有很多人願意付出
But in this person who is willing to give
可是在這個願意付出的人裡面
as he plays more public money games
當他進行更多的公共財的遊戲
Because everyone knows I don't have to pay
因為大家知道我不用付出
I can also benefit
我也可以得到好處
So fewer and fewer people are willing to give
所以願意付出的人越來越少
As a result those who think altruistically
結果那些有利他主義想法的人
He also refused to take out the money
他也就跟著不願意把錢拿出來
what did it become in the end
那到最後變成什麼
In the end it becomes in this game of public wealth
到最後變成在這個公共財遊戲
After he ran 10 times 24
當他跑了10次 24之後
no one wants to pay more
沒有一個人願意再出錢
take a look at this chart
各位看一下這個圖表
This chart is actually very close to the one just now.
這個圖表跟剛剛那個其實是很接近的
is if we don't have participants
就是如果我們沒有參與者
This possibility without any penalty
沒有任何懲罰的這個可能性
this game of public wealth
這個公共財的這個遊戲
when he got to the 10th time
當他走到第10次的時候
willing to give
願意付出的人
This ratio has been decreasing
這個比例是一直下降的
keeps falling
一直下降的
If you keep making him play 20 times
如果你繼續讓他玩20次的話
Hardly anyone wants to throw money away anymore
幾乎沒有人願意再把錢丟出來了
Then if you have this mechanism of punishment
那如果你有這個懲罰的這個機制
That means we are now for the first time
就是說我們現在第一次
first game
第一個遊戲
Then I lose 3 yuan
那我丟3塊錢
No one lost a dime
有人一毛錢都沒有丟
what about me
那我呢
i can punish him
我可以處罰他
i can deduct his money
我可以扣他的錢
what about this time
這個時候呢
this time you can watch
這個時候你可以看
at the eleventh time
在第十一次的時候
When you add this penalty mechanism into
當你把這個處罰的機制加進去
The resources that everyone invests in this public good
大家投入在這個公共財的資源
In the game of public goods
在公共財的遊戲裡面
The possibility that you are willing to take your money out
你願意把錢拿出來的這個可能性
The probability is significantly increased by this ratio
可能性跟這個比例就大幅的提高
Then let me talk about the first
那我先講前面這個
when chileans hang out with altruistic people
當智利的人跟利他的人在一起
Altruistic people are willing to give
利他的人願意付出
But altruistic people may be 30% 40%
可是利他的人可能30% 40%
But 60% of them are from Chile
但是有60%的人他是智利的
totally unwilling to give
完全不願意付出
Altruistic people at this time
這個時候有利他主義的人
he doesn't want to be a fool
他不願意當笨蛋
don't want to be a fool
不願意當傻瓜
So he won't pay anymore
所以他也不會再付出了
so you see here
所以你看到在這裡
Some people are willing to invest a lot of money
開始有人很願意投很多錢
This proportion of increasing investment
越來投入的這個比例
The proportion is getting lower and lower
比例越來越低
It would have been nearly 45%
本來將近有45%
tenth time here
到這裡第十次
about twenty left
剩下差不多二十
It turns out that those who are willing to give selflessly
原來就是那些願意無私的付出的人
altruistic person
利他主義的人
He doesn't want to pay anymore
他不願意再付出了
Then this research has a very important significance
那這個研究它有一個很重要的意義
what does this mean
什麼樣的這個意義呢
When we see this tragedy of so-called public goods
當我們看到所謂的公共財的這個悲劇
When we see that people are very indifferent to public affairs
當我們看到大家對公共事務都非常冷漠的時候
Our first assumption shouldn't be that everyone is selfish
我們第一個假設不應該是每個人都是自私的
our first
我們第一個
we might think about it
我們可能要想一下
At the last moment, everyone is unwilling to pay
到最後那個時間點大家不願意付出
some may be those who are highly altruistic
有些可能是那些具有高度利他主義的人
He's been a fool for too long
他因為當太久的笨蛋
been taken advantage of
一直被人家占便宜
So he was unwilling to continue to do such a thing in the end.
所以他最後他也不願意繼續再做這樣的一件事情
Then this is the research team in Switzerland
那這個是瑞士的這個研究的團隊
His analysis is very important
他分析的很重要
This is an important conclusion
這是重要的一個結論
is when there is no one to give
就是當沒有人要付出
Doesn't mean everyone is Chilean
並不代表每個人都是智利的
There may be two kinds of people
有可能有兩種人
Simply put, there are two kinds of people
簡單的話有兩種人
an altruist
一種是利他主義者
one is chilean
一種是智利人
These two types of behavior may be manifested in the final
這兩種人可能在最後的行為的表現
he's all the same
他都是一樣的
he is indifferent
他都是冷漠的
He is not willing to pay
他都是不願意付出的
But if you watch his process
可是如果你看他的過程
if time moves forward
如果時間往前移的話
at the beginning
在一開始的時候
these altruists
這些利他主義者
probably very very enthusiastic
可能是非常非常熱心的
so what's the point
那這有什麼重要性呢
The importance of this is to say
這個重要性在於說
If you look at the results of the behavior
如果你從行為的結果來看
no one cares about these things
大家都不關心這些事情
Doesn't mean everyone is Chilean
不代表每個人都是智利的
but when needed
可是當有需要的時候
when there is some crisis
當有一些危機出現的時候
these altruists
這些利他主義者
he may come out again
他可能會再站出來
in this public affairs
在這個公共事務的
When public goods are created
公共財的創造的時候
play the leader
扮演那個領導